today we're going to learn how you can
actually price a discrete look back call
option with stochastic volatility using
monte carlo methods we're also going to
be looking at how you can use variance
reduction techniques to further reduce
the standard error around your estimate
so we're going to look at how you can
incorporate anti-tethic variants and
then control variants namely delta gamma
and vega control variants to actually
reduce the standard error of this monte
carlo simulation now we may not have an
analytical solution for this discrete
look back call option with stochastic
volatility but what we do have an
analytical solution for is a
continuously monitored look back call
option with constant volatility we're
going to use that analytical solution to
then uh gauge in our monte carlo
simulation the delta the gamma and the
vega we're then going to use linear
regression to be able to determine what
percentage minimizes the squared error
between our discrete look-back call with
stochastic volatility to the analytical
solution of a continuously monitored
constant volatility look-back call
option so without further ado let's get
into it so first off path dependent
options with a look back option so a
look back option the options payoff are
dependent on extreme so the maximum or
minimum values of the underlying assets
over a certain time period there are two
standard look back options we've got the
fixed strike and the floating strike
today we're going to be looking at the
fixed strike look back options and this
pays the difference if positive between
the maximum or the minimum of the set of
observations over a given look back
period
of the asset price to the strike k at
time t so what does all that mean well
essentially for a fixed strike we've got
k we've got a look back call option that
pays the difference between the maximum
price over those monitoring dates that
we've observed of the stock price minus
k and if that is positive then we get
that value now similarly for the put
what we've got here is for a fixed
strike we get the difference between the
fixed strike and the minimum if positive
so this maximum is just described as the
maximum of the stock price at these
discrete monitoring times and then the
minimum is just the minimum of the stock
price over this path so we're going to
be using the heston model to actually
get this stochastic volatility within
our monte carlo simulation so here
remember we're modeling the square root
variance process so here we've got the
underlying sde under the risk neutral
measure where we've got our
deterministic component and our
diffusion component now the diffusion
component square root variance process
that we're modeling here and we've got
our rate of mean reversion we've got our
theta which is our long run variance and
then we've got sigma which is the
volatility of volatility
so here we've got
our relationship between our two winer
processors so in other words the
correlation between the variance process
and then the stock price and here for
simplicity we're going to assume no
correlation of course we have assumed
correlation before and we've had to use
a cholesky decomposition within our
monte carlo simulation please go back
through some of my previous tutorials on
how you can actually do that so let's
look at our initial parameters here
we've got our initial stock price our
strike price both 100 time to maturity
is just going to be one year we've got a
six percent annual risk free rate 20
volatility we've got a continuous
dividend of three percent now heston
parameters again we've just made these
up but you could use any any kind of
machine learning technique on
actual observed prices in the markets to
be able to derive these and what we've
got is kappa we've got five so the rate
of mean reversion we've got the variance
that we see our initial variance so
that's just our volatility 20
squared our long run is just going to be
and our volatility of volatility our
sigma is going to be 0.02 so let's break
down the monte carlo simulation step by
step so here we're going to go through
for each simulation and then for each
time step now our discrete monitoring
times are going to be at the end of each
week so in our one year period we're
going to have 52 time intervals so let's
assume that we're evenly spaced discrete
look back so here we just have our time
which is just one year divided by the 52
weeks we're going to pre-compute our
constants so we're going to take our
yearly constants that we have and we're
going to times it by dt for our kappa
and then we're going to times it by the
square root of dt to get our adjusted
sigma
so now we've just got some standard
placeholders and these are going to be
used just to accrue
the sum of ct and the sum of ct squareds
so into our monte carlo method for each
simulation we need to initialize our
stock price our initial variance and
then our max that we've observed so here
we generate one of variables and
remember they're uncorrelated so we've
got one that we're using for the
variance process and one that we're
using for the asset process
so here we
actually step out our variance process
and calculate the next variance based on
the current variance using all our
variables and then we do once we have
that variance we can then use that to
actually model our asset process so here
we can take our next stock price which
is just equal to the current stock price
times by the exponential of this drift
term and this diffusion term
now once we've actually stepped through
one place in time we're going to look at
what the current
our new stock price is and if it's
greater than our already observed max
then we're going to set the max equal to
that value and then we step through for
all
52 intervals once we've done that we
compute the max of zero or the payoff
between this max minus this strike and
then what we do is we aggregate our ct
and then the sum of ct squareds
so then we run through all 1000
simulations and then we can compute the
discounted expectation and then we can
also get our standard error using the
sum the sum ct squared and the sum of
cts
we can see here that we get a call value
of 15 dollars with a standard error of
about 0.45 now computation time was
about 0.5
now how do we just do the exact same
thing but actually speed that up well
what we can do is you can use numpy
arrays and vectorize this component it
is important to realize though we are
not going to be able to vectorize the
time solution because we need to know
what the next variance is in the step
before we can actually move forward so
it's still going to be incremented by
time you'll see what i mean in a second
where we get the gain is that we can
vector we can create an array for all
our simulations for each time step
so we have the same pre-computed
constants for the heston model and then
our time
now we're generating one of variables of
size n times m
here we've got arrays for storing our
prices and variance process and we're
just filling in with the initial stock
prices and the initial variance
and then we've got our arrays for
storing the maximum and this is just a
flat array
of m so 1000 variables and again we've
just filled with the initial stock price
now we can just run through each time
period so what we're doing here is we
need to calculate the variance first and
then we calculate the log asset prices
using that variance for each simulation
so we calculate for each simulation 1000
in time j what our next variance step is
and then we can simulate the log asset
prices after we found out what that
variance is at time j
so then we can calculate the
deterministic component and then the
square root variance
process which of course is needed for
determining our stock price in the next
period
once we've done that we've got 1 000
stock prices at that time and we need to
just check across all those thousand
stock prices whether for each one of
those scenarios it's exceeded our
previously observed st max now if it has
along that path exceeded that max then
what we need to do is we're just going
to replace only those values where it's
exceeded it so for and in our first time
step it would just stay as a hundred for
all the ones prices that went down but
for the prices that exceeded 100 they
would be replaced with whatever that
value is
once we run through all time periods
then 52 time periods then we can
calculate the maximum between all of
these observed maximum prices in those
52 week periods minus k if positive then
we can take the discounted expectation
to calculate the option price and here
we get
15.67 so very similar to before and we
get a standard error of 0.44 so exactly
the same as before except we have a
significantly reduced computation time
now let's consider some variance
reduction techniques let's first look at
the antithetic variate so antithetic
variate is just where we have two asset
processes so here we've got two asset
processors that are perfectly negatively
correlated so here i just need to
initialize
two arrays and then two arrays for the
max
we have the same variance process that's
been calculated previously but this time
here we have our diffusion component
whereby the first asset is perfectly
negatively correlated to the second
asset price this is kind of like two for
one we're only simulating uh 1 000
simulations for each of the time steps
however each time step we're actually
getting two
times the benefit because we're using
that variable twice so now we're going
to create that mask and where the price
has respectively
increased over the previously observed
max we replace it and we do the same for
both
the assets 1 and 2. so once we've done
that then we take the expectation
of both of those circumstances so it's
just a half
times by the first circumstance payoff
plus the second so it's like we have a
portfolio of two perfectly negatively
correlated assets
we then just take the discounted
expectation of that payoff of the
portfolio and we can see that we get a
call value
similar to before of 15.77 but now we
have a significantly reduced standard
error of 0.19 so now we're going to look
at a very similar product which we have
an analytical solution for and this is
going to be handy for our control
variants so here we have an analytical
solution for continuous observations
with constant volatility so as we've
said there's no analytical solution for
the price of a european fixed strike
look back call option with discrete
fixings with stochastic volatility under
the hester model however there is a
simple analytical formula for a
continuous
fixing fixed strike look back call with
constant volatility and here is the
solution now i've got a link to a paper
where we have the solution for this
fixed strike look back call and you can
reference it there but essentially i've
created a class where we initialize
the parameters and then we can calculate
the option price and i do have a
vectorized calculation as well as a
non-vectorized solution
so essentially when you have an
analytical solution of course you can
actually just differentiate these
equations with respect to the variable
of interest your sensitivities however
this takes time and it can often be
easier to actually just implement finite
difference methods within your monte
carlo simulation to be able to calculate
your sensitivities so that's what i've
done here
we have
finite difference calculations to be
able to determine the delta the gamma
and then the vega so here as you can see
we can a initialize our instance of the
class with our
parameters that we've defined and then
we've got our continuous call look back
option i can then use the functions that
i've defined to pull out the necessary
bits of information so obviously i want
the option price here so that's just
option price vectorized and then here
i've got our delta fd so finite
difference our gamma and our vega and
here you can see what they are for our
actual time period big t okay so now
that we've got that class and we can
actually reference that analytical
solution and get our sensitivities how
can we actually use that well
essentially here i want to remind you
that we have our general control variant
equation
so here we've got our forward
initial price of the option so this is
the premium this is our payoff and then
this is the discrete hedging that we
have in terms of our control variants
now our control variants are all
calculated individually and are
different between delta gamma and vega
control variants
essentially what we can do
is given data for our particular payoff
situation so we're interested in
discrete hedging
so we're interested in the discrete look
back call option with stochastic
volatility we can get the price and the
payoffs and relate that to
certain control variants of interest so
these are going to be the control in
control variants that we actually
determine from our analytical solution
of the continuous
look back call option with constant
volatility
so we can do that essentially by
creating a monte carlo simulation with
both the control variants from an
analytical solution and then our payoffs
from our stochastic
volatility and then we can use least
squares regression to be able to find
out what the parameters are of each of
those combinations of the variants that
we're going to look at our delta gamma
and vega and then what is best to
minimize the squared error so if that
doesn't make sense that's okay we're
going to run through it here so here is
our calculation of our control variant 1
which is going to be delta now here
we've got the equation
for each of those components and when it
is gbm dynamics therefore we have the
expectation of the next stock price
being this so we're going to code this
up for the black shoals model and we're
going to look at what the relationship
is between delta and the payoff
so here we can use a monte carlo
simulation and step through
time for 52
time intervals with 1000 simulations
then we can plot the sum of the control
variants over time with respect to the
payoff and here we can see a one-to-one
relationship and the reason it's not
crossing zero here is that that beta
zero our intercept is actually
reflective of the forward price of our
initial premium so here we're going to
be using least squares regression so we
can find the true relationship between
the control variant hedging and payoff
and here we can see that we've got numpy
v stack which is just a array of ones
and then we've got our control the sum
of control variants over those 52 weeks
where we've been doing delta hedging
so then we've got a thousand scenarios
and we can see here that it's a
one-to-one relationship or thereabout
with our delta hedging with 52 weeks so
if we delt a hedge and we accrue all
those sums over each week in that
simulation we've got a thousand of them
you end up with this graph here
and we can use least squares regression
to find out the coefficient of best fit
now in the same vein we're going to do
that with a portfolio of delta gamma and
vega
control variants and we're going to see
what that portfolio will be what the
beta values are that minimize uh the
difference between our analytical
solution and then our
look back with
stochastic volatility so we're going to
initialize all our parameters again our
histone parameters
so now we're going to calculate our
fixed strike look back call so our
analytical solution at each time period
we're going to calculate the delta the
gamma and the vega we're going to
simulate our variance process and our
log asset process
with respect to that variance and then
at each time step we use these delta
gamma and vega coefficients to actually
accumulate these control variants over
time we're going to sum them up each
respectively and note they have
different equations here because of the
methodology of how these control
variants actually work within the
geometric brownian
motion framework and then we're going to
compare these to our payoff at the end
of our stochastic volatility look back
option and remember that's just the
difference between our max and our
strike
so once we look at that we can take our
linear least square components and we
can see the relationship between
our payoff
of the stochastic look back call option
and then our delta gamma and vega and
these are what we're going to use as our
control variants going forward to reduce
the error what does that look like well
essentially
so in this diagram you can see the
relationship between the delta the gamma
and the vega based
control variants with respect to the
payoff now that we have an idea of what
they are we can use them then within our
simulation
so now we've got the same
time intervals and then 1000 simulations
so now we have some control varia
constant terms that have come into this
equation and these are determined just
for ease of calculation for our
accumulation of these control variants
so first thing we're going to do if for
each time step we're going to compute
the hedge sensitivities
so here we've got our call price and
we've got our fixed strike look back
call
and this is determined from our current
stock prices at the current time and
then our volatility here which is the
square root of variance we then
calculate our delta gamma vega we
simulate our new variance at time step j
we then simulate our log asset prices at
time step j and then now we accumulate
our control variants over each of these
time periods so we calculate our delta
based control variant our gamma based
control variant and then our vega based
control variant
we then of course check whether our
stock price has exceeded our previously
observed max for that path and then if
so we just replace that
we can then see that we get a call value
of 16.15 with a standard error of 0.2
and the calculation time has gone up
significantly
now we're going to consider what happens
when we have the entity and the control
variant together so here we're doing the
exact same thing except we have two
asset paths as well so now we've got two
call options
with that fixed strike look back call
analytical solution we calculate two
delta processors two gamma processes two
vega processors we simulate the variance
process one variance process and then
use that to actually simulate the next
log asset prices for time step j for
both one and two which are perfectly
negatively correlated against each other
we can then accumulate our control
variants and now remember our control
variants are actually the sum of both
scenarios so we have like two different
portfolios here where we've got our
stock price at two and a stock price one
and each for a thousand times
so now that's for our delta our gamma
and our vega
we then have two masks
which is
we're just checking for our stock prices
if it has exceeded our previously
observed max replace it and then we
compute the expectation and the
expectation is of course the average
between these two scenarios our st1 and
st2
and because we've accumulated st1 and
st2 already within our cv
1 2 and 3 we can just add that in here
and divide by 2.
so we've got our maximum of st 1 max
minus k plus the maximum of
0 and st 2 max minus k plus our beta 1
times cv 1 plus beta2 times cv2 plus
beta3 times cv3 and remember those are
what we calculated out of sample before
using linear regression
here you can see we've got a standard
error of 0.1 and we've got our core
value of 16. now calculation time has
almost doubled we can compare our
calculation times between our slow
estimate fast estimate and then our
reduction in standard error compared to
the antithetic variate control variants
and then the combination of antithetic
and control variants here you can see
that we get about a 4.5 times reduction
in the using the antithetic and control
variant compared to just a normal
non-variance reduction technique
now that does come at a 62 times the the
relative computation time as just a
simple monte carlo simulation so as you
increase the accuracy of this model by
trying to add control variants and
reduction techniques then it's important
to remember that there is a trade-off
with computation time
now the reason the control variants here
haven't
done done nearly as well as in previous
products is because the relationship
between our stochastic model look back
call payoff is not that closely aligned
to our continuously monitored
look back call option with constant
volatility so here you could come up
with a variety of products that might
better fit
the relationship between the payoff that
we're actually trying to model here
so thank you very much for listening i
hope you enjoyed and until next time
youtube see you later